[Music]
hey hey welcome back uh
it's day two of our advanced uh game
design camp
uh excited to have you back a lot of
people fall off after the first day so
we're excited to have you back so today
what we're going to do is we're going to
make a game called dino jump
it's kind of themed after um there's a
game called the no internet game
it's like in chrome if you don't have
internet there's like a dinosaur there i
don't know if you've ever discovered
this it's like this secret in chrome
and you can jump over cactus and things
like that so this game is kind of themed
after that so it's kind of called
dino jump because of that that
inspiration it's a little different
but you can set the idea before we dive
into today let's kind of recap a couple
of the things we learned yesterday
because there were a ton of good skills
in that first day
um one of the big ones um that you may
not have done before
was clones so mckinley actually found
clones uh
new by the way that just reminded me i
should introduce my campers uh let you
know who's here with me today all right
camper number one who are you
i am keegan keegan you ready to go today
yeah
other camper introduce yourself mckinley
fisher are you uh
excited about today's game yes all right
so i just want to let you know that
they're
here with me doing things so yesterday
we learned about clones
that was even new to mckinley right she
hadn't done much with clones
we learned about broadcasting messages
which is a way for two sprites to
communicate
information and there was a bunch of
other things but i won't go into them
i mentioned those two because we're
going to reinforce on those today and
those are definitely skills that we're
going to use today as well
let's start off by looking at a solution
for what we're going to make
so this is bob's uh version uh so bob
schaefer who's the other person in this
uh but what we're doing is we have uh
some hero
and our hero is jumping over um the
obstacles so you can see it's kind of
themed after
kind of themed after uh cactus jump um
the one difference is if you're noticed
i can actually go forwards and backwards
in this game we just think that that
makes it more fun
the no internet game doesn't have that
feature so we have it by the way you can
also um
go forwards and backwards midair uh
that's just to try to make the game more
fun um but you can see that we're gonna
do things like simulating gravity
uh so we're gonna have a jump uh and
we're gonna simulate gravity gravity is
a cool thing
to be able to add to your games but this
is the goal
so one thing i do want to say about
today is that you don't have to use the
sprites that i have here
you don't have to use the sprites we
have here you have to have a hero sprite
um and you have to have an obstacle you
jump over and you have to have a
background
but they can be whatever you want right
so there's no no rules on that today so
think in your head of what your theme is
going to be and that's going to be
useful for today
uh the skills we're going to use are
learned today we're going to use gravity
on our sprite so that'll be kind of a
neat thing
it's not built in it's not magic oh we
just have to figure it out and write the
code for it
we're going to use random numbers we're
going to play sounds we're going to do
more with broadcasting events
and then publishing our games as well
since one of the core
things of this game is gravity i thought
i'd talk about gravity just a little bit
gravity which is also called an
acceleration
it's the force that's put on all bodies
so they fall right so people know about
gravity
since you're a little kid right and the
idea is is that here's a person
who's apparently a stunt man jumping off
a building into an
airbag right and the idea with gravity
is that he jumps
at one point and he has a velocity of
zero
and after he starts falling after one
second he's falling at a certain speed
he's falling like 10
meters per second here and then as he
falls like as he continues to fall
he actually falls not just down but he
falls faster and faster
as he goes down and you'll your eyes are
used to seeing it so like there's this
natural
um kind of slow at the top and then fast
at the bottom and we're going to
simulate gravity uh in our games
he's throwing a bowl all right so keegan
corrected me he said he's throwing a
ball he's not jumping he's just throwing
a ball
that makes a lot more sense all right
moving on
so uh go visit scratch.mit.edu
so here i'm on scratch uh click on
create to start a new game
uh sometimes you can play your old game
for a little bit before you start today
but you can pick a new game and then the
first thing to do is to pick your
your three items uh you can see in the
solution here we had a cat jumping over
a dinosaur
um but you can actually do anything that
you want uh so i'm actually going to
start off by
deleting my cat and then adding some
other sprite
so one way you can add sprites is of
course from the sprite library
uh the sprite library when you hover
over this you can just click on the
circle
or you can click on this magnifying
glass they actually do the same thing
choose a sprite
i'm going to do that for one of my
sprites and then for one of the others
i'm going to upload
just kind of show you how it works so i
think what i'm going to do
is i'm going to go ahead and use a
dinosaur i kind of like this dinosaur
but i'm going to switch it from the
solution and instead of
my dinosaur being the thing that gets
jumped over
my dinosaur is going to do the jumping
so it's going to kind of be like
the dinosaur theme and then the thing i
want to jump over is i want to jump over
a cactus
now the first thing you should do is you
should see is hey is there a cactus
built
into the library well there's not right
so what i'm going to do is i'm going to
go search the internet
for an image of a cactus and then i'm
going to bring it into the game
so to search the internet for a cactus
what you should do is you should do a
google search for cactus
and then what i want is i want images of
cactus so in google you can click on
images here
so now it shows you a bunch of images of
different cacti
for scratch games we don't want so like
see how this one has a
square rectangle sorry a rectangle
that's solid
that would not look very good in our
game what we want is we want something
with a background of transparent
so you can do that in google so you
click on tools
color transparent yeah
so my kids know this game this came
really well
and so this will give you images
that have transparent backgrounds and
now you can go through and you can find
what you want
um other tricks you can use by the way
is if you kind of want something with a
more cartoony look
uh and type you can go to clip art and
it'll give you kind of like more
cartoony things sometimes
cartoony drawings look better in scratch
because it goes with um
with the built-in sprites better and you
can just find
a cactus that you want um so i'm just
going to click on this one
you hope that it really does have a
transparent background that should show
up as this checkerboard pattern
some people on the internet are tricky
though they put a real black and white
background on there to make it look like
it's transparent
we're just going to hope that it worked
out and then what i do is i right click
on it and i say
save image as and i'm just going to call
it
cactus and then in my game
i'm going to come over here to choose a
sprite but instead of just clicking the
circle i'm going to use this
top one which says upload sprite and i'm
going to select
that cactus now you never know what size
it's going to come in
it doesn't matter if it comes in huge
that's really no big deal
because you can always just go to the
size here and you can make it smaller
so for mine i'm gonna have to make it
smaller still
um i guess i'll make it about that big
that seems that seems about right
so my dinosaur is gonna have to jump
over these uh different cactus
and you can play with your size uh until
you're happy with things
yeah he's about right maybe i'll make my
dinosaur a little bigger
uh cool all right so i think that i'm
happy with this uh i need oh i need a
backdrop is what i need
so let's go ahead and open up backdrops
so the backdrop you can actually click
right here on choose a backdrop
um or you can come over here to costumes
and you can click on choose a backdrop
over here
it's funny it's for backdrop it's
basically the same button regardless of
which side you use
um and i'm going to just go ahead and
put in uh the desert theme uh that fit
pretty well
uh with what i'm after all right so at
this point i've got
uh my cactus i've got my dinosaur
and what i want to do is i want you to
kind of set them uh where you think
ground level should be
so i'm going to put my cactus right
there towards kind of planting the
ground
and my dinosaur toward his feet are just
barely on the ground
now i'm ready to come in and start my
code
so the first thing we want to do for
our hero so whatever's doing the jumping
so my hero
is the dinosaur he's going to be doing
the jumping is we want him to
uh do things when the green flag is
clicked
and what we're actually going to focus
on first with him is uh
falling right so we want him to to be
good at falling
falling is something that's going to
happen to where his y position is going
to change
up until he gets to ground level right
and when he gets to ground level he
stops
right now uh make sure your hero is
selected and look at the
the y value in here so your y value will
be different than mine
but for me my ground level is negative
115. so find yours and figure it out
that number is going to be useful
throughout our game so what i'm going to
do is i'm actually going to make a
variable
so click on variables then click on make
a variable
you can say for this sprite only so this
variable is going to be for the ground
level
and it really only affects this one one
sprite
and i'm just going to call it ground
level
you can see how i like to name my
variables i like to leave no spaces and
capitalize
the next level next letter it's just a
choice
that i choose to make but you really
could do just about anything
ground level defaults by being displayed
on the screen i don't want it displayed
on the screen
so i'm going to hit this check box and
not have it get displayed on the screen
and this variable is kind of a funny
variable because i'm just going to set
it one time
to negative 115 for me
and i'm just going to use that variable
a couple times so variables have a
couple different purposes
sometimes they're used as something you
like set and change like a score keeper
we're going to use the score keeper in
this game as well
but this variable is a little different
this variable is what's called it's to
help me avoid magic numbers in my code
so instead of having this magic negative
appear like different places in my code
i'm making it once as variable
all right long speech for for not much
good there
so let's go ahead and have the the
dinosaur
start in some position so i like to
always make him
start at a certain x y
so if i put this in he's of course going
to start at ground level which is fine
since we're currently simulating falling
i'm going to actually start him up here
just so that we can practice with with
falling right
so up there you can see now his y is 72
so i'm going to say make his y be
72. all right to make him fall we're
going to need a forever loop
so let's just go ahead and grab a
forever loop and drag it over
um and in this forever loop what we want
to do is we want his
y to get smaller and smaller and smaller
so in motion
let's go ahead and find change y by
so change y by
and right now to start things off we're
just going to say negative 1. so we're
going to change the y by negative one
every time this loop goes around if you
were to run it now
he would start falling right so he's
falling at a very slow speed
and he's falling at a very constant rate
and he does not stop when he hits the
ground
he does stop before he goes off the
screen that's a feature that scratch
does to try to be friendlier to you
it won't let you push things off the
screen because it's very confusing like
where did it go
um so it's a start right so it's too
slow
um and it doesn't use gravity because
it's a constant velocity which is not
how gravity works
and it doesn't stop the bottom so we got
to fix all these things
let's fix them one at a time let's fix
um let's fix
doesn't fall through the ground first
right so
for doesn't fall through the ground uh
what i want to do is i like to practice
with functions
we're going to make a function so click
on my blocks
click on make a block
and we're just going to call this
function check for
ground
we didn't have to make a function here
but i just like to practice with
functions right
so the ideas with functions is um you
know after you do your movement
then you check for the grounds so this
calls the function
and then the things that are going to be
inside the function is it's just going
to check the y
to see if it's below ground level right
so to check
something we need an if statement so
we're just going to say
if and the thing we want to check is we
want to check my y
value to see if it's less than ground
level
so we need an operator to do a greater
than less than
and if my y y is a built-in variable
it's inside motion
so y position is what it's called so if
my y position
is less than ground level i've got a
variable for ground level
so if that ever happens that means i'm
below ground
then i want to set my y to be ground
level
so i'm going to go to motion
and i'm going to find set y
oops where's set y
and i'm going to set it to this variable
ground level
and you can see how using this variable
makes your code more readable right
because i mean if you read this it says
check for ground if y position less than
ground level
so if you're less than ground level then
set
y to ground level and i really like how
scratch does a nice job of naming the
blocks
to where you kind of know what's going
to happen just based on reading them
so you can see that when i ran at this
time he again very slowly fell
but he stopped when he got to the ground
does that sound good
campers are you doing all right all
right i'm gonna pause for a second help
my campers
all right i checked in my campers that
are doing good i'm excited about their
themes i'll show you i'll show you what
they're up to later
all right so the next thing i want to do
is i want to actually uh you know
simulate how gravity works right
where the velocity actually gets bigger
uh
the farther you go down instead of the
word velocity which is the word that i
like to use that's the technical term
let's just call it fall speed so first
thing i want to do is over here i want
to make a variable
i'm going to call it fall speed i'll
tell you what since i
am going to show this to the world i'm
going to put it on the screen
i'm going to name it differently right
so this is how i name things when
they're like
visible to the world so this is my fall
speed
also this variable is literally just for
this sprite
but i'm going to do something tricky i'm
going to say it's for all sprites
just because whenever you put it on the
screen it's super ugly if you say
for all sprites you can see it's like
dinosaur four colon blah blah blah blah
so i'm gonna say it's for all sprites
even though it's not
um just so that when it displays up here
it displays prettier
so that's another reason you might want
to do for all sprites all right so i'm
going to
set the full speed to be initially zero
so i'm just going to do that right at
the top so the fall speed is zero so
he's not
he's not falling he's not jumping he's
just not moving right now
and then what i'm going to do is i'm
going to inside the forever loop
i'm going to change the fall speed by
negative one
and so what that does is that means that
you
fall faster and faster and faster the
longer you fall
so that makes like this value is 10 here
and then by the time it gets down to
here it's 20.
so my fall speed just gets faster and
faster and faster
and then i'm going to change y by my
fall speed
so that y changes depending on what the
full speed is
uh and so now it'll be a subtle
difference but as you uh click play
um your hero will actually start falling
um faster the longer he falls um if you
want to start them even higher uh maybe
i'll start him at like 160.
maybe i could see it better um but he
actually like kind of has this like
acceleration as he gets to the ground
now there is a problem if you're
watching closely the fall speed um
claims to keep going right and that's
just because that's what our code did
and the trick is is that it claims to
keep going but he doesn't move because
we have check for ground in here
that does kind of bug me though that
that number is going out of control
so we will fix it don't don't worry
about that we will fix it
before we fix it though i actually want
to do a left and right motion first
so like if i hit left arrow nothing
happens if i hit right arrow nothing
happens
i'm going to fix that first and then i'm
going to come back and fix this problem
so left and right arrow we need to check
if you're pressing the left arrow
or if you're pressing the right arrow so
see if you can do this one on your own
so for the dinosaur
and what i want you to do is if you are
pressing the left arrow
then i want you to change your x by some
negative amount
and if you're pressing the right arrow
change your x by some positive amount
see if you can do this one all by
yourself
all right so so my camper's got it but i
did have to to help a little bit
i'm not expecting if you're new to this
for you to be able to do it on your own
i just wanted you to try
right um but the idea is is that we're
going to need two if statements
i'm going to go ahead and drop my if
statements right into the forever loop
here
and so we're going to need to check for
left key press and right key press so
left and right
this is actually very similar to what we
did last time checking for left and
right arrows
and then what we're going to do is we're
going to change the x
by some amount you could also use the
move by
but i choose to to do change x and y so
i don't change
directions right so left should be a
negative and then i can can give it a go
so
i should be able to press the right
arrow key and move
to the right and the left arrow key and
move to the left by the way keegan
mentioned that you can actually
uh move while you're falling uh he says
that that's not how
you know physics really works um and i
said that's how our game works uh so
moving
while falling makes it more fun right so
just kind of know that
that is how we choose to implement our
game
all right so now we're going to fix this
problem of
we keep falling even when we're on the
ground
this is actually going to be the
trickiest part of today's code
because it's going to involve shuffling
around our code some
right so here's what i want you to do i
want to shuffle around
the code sum what i want to do is the
thing that makes you fall is these two
lines here this
change fall speed by negative 1 and this
change y by fall speed
and so what i want to do is i want to
pull those two out and set them over
here
and then just leave everything else
alone so what i'm going to choose to do
is i'm going to choose to drag
everything over and then i'm going to
put back
just this part so now i kind of have
this this hanging out over here
if i were to run my code right now uh it
would not really work very well because
i would no longer be falling i could
still go to the left and right when i'm
way up here
but i took out falling temporarily right
we're going to put it back
so now what i want to do to put it back
is i want to determine
if i'm on the ground or not because if
i'm on the ground
then i can do things like jump if i'm
not on the ground then i need to
to do this code right here which is fall
so i'm going to actually grab
an if else statement uh and stick it in
here
so mckinley was like throwing her hand
up she wanted to say what we needed for
this
and so i want to have an if else
statement
and so now i've got to put in here a
question
that'll determine if i'm on the ground
or not right so i just want to ask some
question
that says hey am i on the ground and the
question that i want to ask is
is my y value equal to that ground value
so if i want to test if things are equal
that's in operators
so i need to grab the equals operator
and i want to check to see is my
y position equal to
that variable called ground level you
can see how we use that variable called
ground level a few times in our code so
if the y
position is equal to ground level so if
they are equal
this top area means i'm on the ground if
i'm on the ground i don't fall
so this code right here goes into the
bottom
so it goes into the bottom because if
i'm not on the ground
then i want to fall right so let's go
ahead and run our code again
and he should fall up until he hits the
ground and then
and then he stops if you wanted to uh
you could also add
um when you're on the ground you could
say set full speed to zero so
this will mean that when you're on the
ground you're no longer falling so it's
zero
so this would make it even better so now
he falls and then when he hits the
ground he stops
and this actually is very true to
physics because you hit the ground and
you're going
really fast and then you just
immediately come to a stop
right which can hurt but you can see
this really simulates physics
now the next thing we want to do is i
want to be able to uh
to jump right so like i want to be able
to press the space bar
to jump right now i don't have any way
to jump right
so what i want to do is inside this area
here and this is always tricky when
you're putting code in a certain spot
inside this area here which means i'm on
the ground i want to check for the space
bar
so i've got to go grab an if statement
so control if
for better for worse scratch makes this
sometimes tricky but i want to drop it
right here
right so it's after the fall speed not
not inside of it which would be there
i want to put it right after and in here
so i'm on the ground my fall speed is
currently zero
i want to check for the space bar
so i want to find key pressed uh space
the default was was right for once
and if that happens then i want to jump
right so how how do i jump
really all jumping is in this game is
jump is
is making your fall speed be a positive
number and then that way your fall speed
is going up
so what we're going to do to jump is
we're going to set the fall speed
to some positive number i don't really
know the right positive number
but this number determines how high you
jump
i'm going to start off with 20. if 20
turns out to be a really short jump
then i'll make it bigger if 20 turns out
to like jump me off the top of the
screen then i'll make it smaller
right and in jumping we have to uh
do the very first start of the jump so
we're going to
change y
by the fall speed
and what this does is this will get you
off the ground
so in our code it's important that we
get ourselves off the ground so this is
the first part of your jump so you
you're rearing back and you say my full
speed is 20 and so we're going to move
you up
those 20 pixels and then after you're
off the ground then falling should start
taking effect
so there's a lot of complexities in the
code here but if it all works
um you should be able to uh perceive
jumping
so there i jumped and you can see how it
feels like a jump
because you start fast and then you go
so slow at the top to the point where
you actually stop
for one moment at the very top of the
jump and then you come back down
and it actually turns out that 20 was a
really good guess so 20
makes me jump uh not quite off the
screen but pretty high
if you want to tweak it a little bit so
you jump a little higher that's fine
if you don't like jumping this high you
can jump a little lower but i think i'm
pretty happy with 20.
another thing that i'm going to do is
now that i can jump
i don't need to do this initial fall
anymore so i'm actually going to start
at
my y of ground level so i'm just
choosing to start
my game just right on the ground no no
no initial fall
just because i can now jump so there's
no reason to start off up in the air
cool i haven't saved my game yet it
seems like a really good time to save my
game
i'm going to call mine cactus jump
you can call yours whatever you want i
think the solution
which which i did with bob it's called
dyno jump because we were jumping over
dinosaurs
um but this time i'm jumping over a
cactus uh so i'll do that
you can see that the next thing that his
game does is he's got these dinosaurs
right
um and these dinosaurs are coming up a
cat all the time
and they obviously score points so you
can see my score is four right now
and they score points whenever you
successfully get a dinosaur to the edge
and then the game ends when you run into
the dinosaur right
with some loud sound effects so that's
what we're trying to do next
so you can see the first thing is
there's many dinosaurs but if we go into
bob's code
by the way you can go into people's code
you can see that there is in fact only
one dinosaur so
we're clearly using clones right that's
the only way you could have multiple
sprites on the screen
and only one dinosaur so this concept of
cloning
we're going to use it again so
similar to what we did last time with
cloning i'm going to clone the cactus
in my case so the cactus is going to
have
a when i start as clone
um and if you remember what we did last
time is the original
we actually are going to eventually hide
the original
and so the first thing that you do in a
clone is you
show it sometimes you can set
its x before you show it but in general
that's something that's going to have to
happen
speaking of setting its x and y where
should the cactus start at right
it should probably start as far as you
can get it over on the right side
so take your your cactus or whatever
your thing is
and make sure it's at ground level and
start it as far to the right as you can
get it so you can just kind of like
scoot it over
until it's like barely even showing that
is where i want each clone to start so
i'm going to go into motion
and i'm going to select go to xy
i'm going to choose to put it just
before my show
that way there's really no risk of like
seeing the cactus in multiple positions
so i'm just going to put it before my
show
and then what my cactus is going to do
is he's going to move across the screen
so to move across the screen we're going
to have to do some things forever
and to move across the screen i'm going
to go to motion
i'm going to go ahead and use change x
by
and so i'm going to change x by negative
3.
and so my goal here is to to see if i
can get this working
and then once i can see if i can get it
working then i'll make it better
so right now i have when i start as
clone go to that position
show myself uh and then start moving
across the screen
there's going to be more code but that's
enough to get us started
if we were to run the game right now
though nothing would happen
because we we didn't make any clones yet
right so nothing happens because we
haven't made a clone
so the question is who makes the clones
right so somebody's got to make the
clones and put them on the screen
many people can make the clones mckinley
who do you think should make them
the stage yeah i like to have the stage
make them so i'm going to actually go
over to the stage
and i like to have him create the clones
and kind of like put things out into the
world
it just feels like a good job for him
mckimley you got a plan
oh one of the stages of her sorry i
should say
then she can start as many clones as you
want thank you for cleaving me
politically correct this
all right she's a stinker so the stage
is going to have a wind green flag
clicked
and it's going to have a forever
and then it's going to um create a clone
and then wait
or wait and then create a clone it
doesn't really matter what you do
i'm going to wait and then create a
clone
maybe i'll crank out a dinosaur every
two seconds
or sorry a cactus so when the green flag
is clicked
i'm going to forever wait for two
seconds and then create a dinosaur
i guess you could do it in either order
it's just a matter of whether you want a
second when your game starts or whether
you want to just go
right so either is fine so if i hit the
stop and then the play button now i
should hopefully have uh
oh i said dinosaur didn't even say
dinosaur i meant to say cactus
i was creating clones of my my dinosaur
which were all right on top of one
another which was not what i wanted
um so there you can see that my cactus
are now coming out
uh every two seconds right now i can
blow right through them
but this is a good time to check to see
if your game is too hard
personally i consider this a little too
hard
so i'm going to change my game some
i'm going to make it 4 seconds
now there's a couple things that we
still need to fix so i think my game got
a lot easier
uh which is good um but i think that my
game is
is just a little boring right so the
cactus come out at exactly the same time
they run at exactly the same speed um
there's a good chance that i could play
this game forever
um and so i know i'm not actually
hitting me up but i'm pretending like i
would be hitting them
so i want to make my game more fun uh
and so as the software design
developer it's up to you to make a game
fun now people are always tempted to
make their game impossible
right like shoot them out as fast as you
can turns out that's not fun
um or they make it too easy that's not
fun either
you've got to pick the right amount of
hard so to make my game more fun i'm
going to introduce some randomness
so instead of making them every four
seconds
i'm gonna pick a random number to where
it's like
two to five seconds right or maybe two
to four is plenty
that way they're going to come out at
different intervals so you never really
know how often to expect them
and their speed instead of making it
always be three
i'm going to make it variable as well
now you can't
what you want to do is you i know you
want to put this right there but don't
do that because that would mean
that like he just changes the speed all
the time we want to make a variable for
him so that you can set it once and then
he'll always be that speed
so go to variables uh make a variable
this time we definitely want to check
for this sprite only
this is important because then each
clone can have its own speed
and i'm just going to call it speed
speed so for this sprite only speed and
this is on my cactus this is the thing
that's being jumped over
and i'm going to set speed
at the top make sure you get the right
variable because like i don't want to
change
full speed that's not my job here um and
i'm going to set it to
some random value so you can see before
it was negative 3
um so i'll go from i don't know maybe
negative five
to negative two i don't know it just
depends on what's fun maybe i'll go in
even bigger range negative six to
negative two so
some of them are gonna shoot out like
fireballs and then others are gonna be
pokey
and they might even like overlap in
crazy ways so
i created this variable called speed
i set it to a random number now i need
to use it
so i'm going to use speed right
inside here and notice that it's
negative so it's going to move
to the left i don't need to show it up
here so i'm going to uncheck this box
and now i can see if my game is actually
fun and playable
again i can't die in it but that's okay
it's a good way
to kind of learn things so you can see
that that guy came out uh
slow and pokey um and so i had two
really slow and pokey
that was actually kind of impossible uh
but that's okay
um i think that for me uh the game might
be fun right
now so occasionally there's things that
happen that make it really hard so
there's a slow one
um oh and then there's a fast one right
after i think for me that's a good
um level of difficulty you can play
yours and you can decide what is what is
appropriate for you
right is it too easy is it too hard
because you don't want to play for an
hour
right but you also want to have a chance
uh there i had to do a double jump
all right i think mine's good um all
right so what we need to do next let's
hide
you can see how there's like a little
cactus hanging over here that's the
original right
so whenever you use clones like this
it's very common to hide the original
um and so you can see that now there's
no like little cactus over there
all right i think the next thing i want
to do is i want to
make it to where if i actually hit a
cactus something bad happens
or whenever it gets over here something
good happens either one
could be implemented next and that's
code that's going to happen
inside the cactus so inside the cactus
we really need
two if statements so we're going to say
i'm in in my cactus the thing that's
getting jumped over i'm going to add two
if statements
because i want to check to see if i made
it to the edge um
or if i've hit the the hero right
so let's go ahead and do the edge first
it doesn't really matter
so the edge we're going to see if our x
value has gotten less than some number
so if you remember the screen it goes
from positive 180 to negative 180
and so if my x value gets below like
somewhere over here i'm going to say
negative i don't know 160.
i don't want to do 180 because because
you can see how
the cactus don't quite get to the very
edge they actually like
stop before they get too far so you
could play with it
but i think that 160 is probably going
to be safe enough once they're past 160
it's safe to delete them right so i want
to see
if their x value so the x value is in
motion
x position so if the cactus
x position is ever less than negative
it means it's gotten all the way to the
left then i want to
score points and i want to play a little
sound
just to let them know they did good uh
the order doesn't
matter um i'm going to play a sound
first the sound that i want to play
i'm going to have to add a sound called
coin
and so i've now added the sound coin to
my sound library now i can use it in my
code
so i'm just going to say start sound
coin
sometimes you want to start sound or
play sound until done
other times you just want to start it i
don't think it matters this time i'll
tell you what we'll
switch it to play until done that'll
actually be better because i'm going to
delete it
as soon as the sound finishes so this
will help me make sure that the sound
finishes
so i did switch it to play sound coin
until
done and then as soon as it's done i
want to score a point
so i go to variables i'm going to have
to make a variable called score
this one is going to be visible on the
screen and so i'm going to make it for
all sprites
and i'm going to make it pretty because
it's going to be visible on the screen
so that i've got full speed and i've got
score
by the way if you don't want full speed
visible anymore i think we're kind of
past that you can hide it if you want
that's that's up to you whichever
whatever you prefer
um and so now i've got this variable
score um i'm going to need to do
the different tasks with it i need to
set it to zero
somewhere and then i need to also
increment it somewhere
i'm going to choose to increment it
right here after i play a coin
or before i play a coin it doesn't
matter i'll do it before
so i'm going to change score by one
we also need to set the score to zero
somewhere
see if you can figure out where would be
a good place
to set the score to zero so i'll let you
see if you can do that on your own see
if you can find a good place for it
all right so i had to go uh quiz my
campers too but the question is um
where do you want to set score to zero
when the game starts
um and it's a trick question because it
basically the answer is
anywhere except for here right because
because here
is when i start his clone which happens
all the time you want
somewhere that happens only one time so
you can put it on your hero
where he has a wind green flag clicked
or you could put it on your stage
doesn't matter which one you do
but it cannot be in this code so i need
to set it to zero
in one of these places so i'm gonna put
it on my stage
but it works just as well on your hero
sprite so i'm gonna say
set score to zero all right back to my
code on the cactus
all right so i say change score by one
play the coin sound until done and then
the last thing i want to do is i want to
delete this clone so i'm i'm done with
them right so i can delete this clone
so i go ahead and hit play and so now
whenever they get to the edge they
should disappear
i can see that 160 was actually a little
conservative
um maybe i should have picked that
better let me just see
i'm going to make my cactus visible for
just a minute if i wanted i could
probably let them go until there
negative two four two
oh i know what i did wrong the x goes to
negative two forty whoops
so yeah so 160 was just straight ah
negative 160 was just the wrong number
um so i should have done like negative
um 2 um 30.
negative 230 be good all right so that
hopefully uh fixes my problem
um and then of course i showed my
original again so i've got to get rid of
my original
but that that seems like it's working
pretty well all right my original
the funny thing is is it doesn't even
matter where your original is
i'm going to plant my original up here
and hide him
because it doesn't matter where he's at
because he's hidden anyway
cool so i think mine is working pretty
well my coin sound is super loud
uh but that's fine and so every time it
gets over there
you can see it scores a point and it
plays the coin sound
now the next thing i want to do is i
want to make it actually like hit my
dinosaur
so i'm going to need to add code to do
that
so i'm going to say if i'm hitting my
dinosaur
then something happens and the thing i
want to do
is i want to go to sensing
[Music]
and i want to grab touching and right
now it says mouse pointer but i want to
switch that to whatever my hero is
so touching dinosaur 4.
now whenever we hit the hero which my
heroes called dinosaur 4
i don't like that name i wish i was just
called dinosaur
so i could change that so now whenever
i'm touching the dinosaur
what do i want to have happen well i
really just want to broadcast an event
so i want to tell
all the rest of the world i just hit the
dinosaur right so we're just going to
broadcast
hit is our plan so that's in events
and we're going to broadcast the message
um
and i'm going to type in hit if you want
to type in a slightly different name
that's fine
but i use hit all the time so we just
broadcast
hit and then every single sprite
is gonna listen for hits the way you
listen for hit is you say when i receive
um hit and one of the most common things
you do is
you stop all your other scripts so i'm
going to actually come down to
it says stop all i find this confusing
it says stop all
but you switch it to stop other scripts
in the sprite
so whenever there's a hit all the cactus
clones
they're gonna all stop their other
script so stop what you were doing
before
these two lines actually need to be in
everybody's code
um one way that i like to copy is that
you can actually just drag and drop it
so i can drop it there and now over in
my dinosaur
there's there's some code in here so he
has a when i receive hit
stop other scripts i also want to drag
and drop it onto the stage
so if i go into the stages code he also
has it
and this is pretty common uh way to use
events so whenever somebody broadcasts
this event
everybody stops what they were doing
before
including the cactus including the stage
including the dinosaur
and then it is the end of the game so
it'd be good to
play some sound to let them know that
the game is over
so let's go to sound actually i'll
probably have to add a sound
so you're going to have to add some
sound i don't care what sound you add
i'm going to go see what dr bob added he
added oops so i'm going to add a sound
called oops
i didn't search for it very well i guess
i'll have to manually search for it
oops is right here if you want to put in
a different sound that's fine
but i'm going to play oops until done
and then i'm going to
stop all so if this works
my game should be complete so i'm now
able to jump over a cactus and score
points
but if i run into a cactus i'm going to
run into the next one
it does the oops and then it ends the
game
so i'm actually done with my game which
is cool
when i finish a game uh what i like to
do is i like to click on
share and that makes my public page
and i'll say use the arrow keys
to move left and right
and then i'll say use spacebar uh to
jump
and i like to put in some instructions
uh for my users
and now i've got this url that i can
send to friends and family
all right so i think my game is done um
i will probably play it one more time
just kind of like make sure that things
are good and then i'm going to help my
campers finish
and then i'm going to show on a video uh
what it looks like
hopefully yours is coming together all
right campers let's see how you did
all right mr keegan you're up first what
have you got for your game today
uh dogs and vacuum cleaners a dog and a
vacuum cleaner
all right let's see your dog let's see
you get over a vacuum cleaner cool
what inspired you oh that's a tricky one
jump them both nice
what inspired you to do dogs and vacuum
cleaners
looks great bud um i didn't hear a sound
when you lo oh no that was your
sound wasn't it all right mckinley let's
see what you've got today
so this one's mine i modified it so i
don't press space to jump i press the up
key
so that my fingers can just be over here
so you've got a hummingbird
uh jumping over snake enemies which is
cool
and then yours is set with the uh the
release interval oh man this is probably
gonna be a tricky one
job did you guys enjoy the uh the game
today yes
do you enjoy the no internet game as
well yeah
cool nicely done uh all right so the
things i kind of wanted to say at the
end uh
that the main message of this camp is
coding is fun and you can do this right
it takes a little bit of time it takes
practice
the more time you put into it the better
you get it we also kind of learned again
you can use cool math skills to do
things
this time it was gravity and how to make
things look like they're falling
appropriately
we also learned how to create uh clones
again
we have one sprite but actually many of
them and how broadcasting events can be
used to communicate
thanks for joining us we look forward to
seeing you again tomorrow bye